<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A true discourse vvherin is set downe the wonderfull mercy of God, shewed towardes the Christians, on the two and twenty of Iune. 1593 against the Turke, before Syssek in Croatia. Truly translated out of the high Dutch coppie. Printed at Vienna.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1593</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 11 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A18694</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 5202</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S109846</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99845489</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99845489</idno>
            <idno type="VID">10394</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A18694)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 10394)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 192:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A true discourse vvherin is set downe the wonderfull mercy of God, shewed towardes the Christians, on the two and twenty of Iune. 1593 against the Turke, before Syssek in Croatia. Truly translated out of the high Dutch coppie. Printed at Vienna.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by [J. Windet for] Iohn Wolfe,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1593.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Formerly STC 6912.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Turkey --  History --  1453-1683 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Syssek (Croatia) --  Siege, 1593 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:10394:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:10394:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A true diſcourſe vvher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>IN IS SET DOWNE THE WONDER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full mercy of God, ſhewed towardes the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, on the two and twenty of Iune. 159<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. againſt the Turke, before Syſsek in Croatia.</p>
            <p>Truly tranſlated out of the high Dutch Coppie. Printed at Vienna<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON Printed by Iohn Wolfe, 1593.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb facs="tcp:10394:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:10394:2"/>
            <head>A TRVE DISCOVRSE, WHEREIN IS ſet downe the wonderfull mercy of God, ſhewed to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes the Chriſtians, on the two and twentie of Iune. 1593. againſt the Turke, before Syſſek in Croatia.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>Pon the 14. day of Iune, that Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian enemie, and Common violator of peace <hi>Haſſam Baſſa</hi> of <hi>Boſſna,</hi> with the reſt of his Lordes and ſouldiers, to the nomber of thyrtie eight thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand and two hundred, ſurpriſed the caſtle and towre of <hi>Trentſchina,</hi> ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times belonging to the Biſhopricke of <hi>Agram.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From thence, vppon the 15. following, he marched before <hi>Syſſek,</hi> and played vpon it with his artillerie, vntill the eightenth day, with ſuch force, that he ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>threw euen to the ground, the towre thereof, and two peeces of ordinance, together with the maſter gunners which were appointed, for among ſuch field peeces as he there vſed, he had three in chief, which ſhot bollets of fortie, four and fortie, &amp; fiue and fortie pound weight.</p>
            <p>Vpon this the borderers of the Empire, drawen thereunto partly by neceſſitie, and partly through de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to relieue <hi>Syſſek</hi> aforeſaid, aſſembled their forces together ouer againſt <hi>Agram</hi> as namely <hi>Rupertus</hi> Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron of <hi>Eckhenberg</hi> generall of the field: <hi>Andrea Awer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperg</hi> chief commander in <hi>Croatia: Erdody Baan</hi> Lord of <hi>Carlſtat</hi> in <hi>Windiſmarke,</hi> the Lord of <hi>Graſwein,</hi> Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronell of the horſemen of <hi>Styria</hi> and <hi>Carniola,</hi> and <hi>Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chior</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:10394:3"/> of <hi>Roderne</hi> Chieftaine of the Ruitters of <hi>Syleſia,</hi> to the number of fiue hundred the <hi>Kopprainitzers</hi> alſo, and the Eſtates of <hi>Windiſmarke</hi> were preſent likewiſe: who leauing two hundred footemen for the defence of <hi>Agram,</hi> and two hundred were for the Sconce (made vpon the bridge), marched forwarde in the name of God: &amp; about midnight (being the eightenth of Iune,) came before <hi>Syſſek,</hi> to the number of foure thouſand fiue hundred men.</p>
            <p>Vpon the ninetenth following, the Turks aſſaulted it: but effectuated nothing, onely they loſt ſome three ſcore Turkes: at which inſtant, our men behaued themſelues manfully.</p>
            <p>Vpon the 20. day <hi>Baſſa</hi> ſent out three hundred men, to ſee if they could intercept any perſon, by whom they might be enformed of the ſtate of our Campe: againſt whom the Baron of <hi>Ecke<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>berg</hi> made out ſome foure hundred horſes, who preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly put the Turkes to flight, of whom, they ſlewe ſome, ſome other were take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and brought home about ſome fortie horſe.</p>
            <p>Vpon the 21. day, there iſſued out agayne on th'other ſide of the water, ſome foure hundred of the enemy, likewiſe to learne and harken of our precee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, who were in like manner beaten backe, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to retire to their Campe.</p>
            <p>Who becauſe they could not paſſe the water, with conuenient ſpeede, loſt many of their companie, <hi>viz:</hi> two ſhippefulls in the water, which were drowned, at which time our men tooke two enſeignes, and one <hi>Agga,</hi> or Coronell, (who had the leading of ſeuen en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeignes).</p>
            <p>Vpon the two and twentith of Iune, our men mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched
<pb facs="tcp:10394:3"/> neere <hi>Syſſek</hi> &amp; entred the Iſlande, againſt whom, th'enemy preſently made head: whoſe great power and force, when our men had perfectly viewed and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined, ſome were of opinion to make a retraitte, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeming it, no point of wiſedome to put themſelues into ſuch an apparant and manifeſt daunger. But the Baron of <hi>Eckenberg,</hi> with certaine other of the Lordes and Chiefe Commaunders, were of a contrary aduiſe, and thought it more conuenient (in Gods name) to try the fortune of the Battaile, eſpecially, becauſe the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie vrged, &amp; they of <hi>Syſſek</hi> were not able one howre lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger to endure the ſiege. Beſides, it was to be feared, leſt th'enemy, in making their retraicte, would vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly ſet vpon them. Which aduiſe allowed and approued of the reſt, they put themſelues in order of battaile. The enemy did the like. And as <hi>Haſſam Baſſa</hi> of <hi>Boſsna</hi> made head againſt our men, with ſome ten thouſand horſe and more, and was now entred the Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land and brought all his Ruitters before <hi>Syſsek,</hi> he cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed his Turkiſh footemen to be placed vpon th'other ſide of the Riuer (where a bridge was made of ſhippes) and the greater part of the Armie kept it ſelfe cloſe in a Troupe.</p>
            <p>The fight began about eleue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or twelue of the clock: And the L. <hi>Baan</hi> with his <hi>Hungarians,</hi> and the people of <hi>Windiſmarke</hi> gaue the firſt aſſault: who through the force and multitude of th'enemy, and namely of the <hi>Ianizaries,</hi> who were placed next the riuer, iſſued out vpon them ſo forcibly, that they were fayne to retire, who neuertheleſſe were reſcued and relieued by the Lord <hi>Graffen</hi> of <hi>Monte Kukulle,</hi> and the harquebuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of <hi>Carniola.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:10394:4"/>
            <p>Vpon th'other ſide the <hi>Koppreunitzers,</hi> they of <hi>Carle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtat,</hi> the <hi>Stirians,</hi> and <hi>Carniolans,</hi> to the number of three hundred horſe, brake vpon th'enemy: emongſt whom was the L. Generall of <hi>Eckenberg,</hi> with the Lordes of <hi>Roderne</hi> and <hi>Sileſian</hi> Ruitters, and the Cheefe Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunders of the horſe, who likewiſe made their fight.</p>
            <p>Now as ſone as the Turkes eſpied them, and found them by their manner of riding, to be of <hi>Carlſtat,</hi> High Almaines, and of the Confines (for they were at the firſt perſuaded, that they had beene, as in times paſt, but Boures and Peſants) they tooke their flight to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes the Bridge, right ouer againſt their Leaguer on the other ſide of the Riuer of <hi>Kulpa:</hi> amongſt whom our people brake in with a great fury. As ſoone as the <hi>Haſſam Baſſa</hi> eſpied this he ran in all haſt to the Bridge made vpon the Riuer <hi>Kulpa,</hi> hoping there to make his people (who were now in Flight) preſently to retourne to the Fight, but all in vaine: for there were about two Enſignes, or fiue hundred Turkes, which had allrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy paſt the Bridge, vnto the Footemen there, and the reſt endeuoured to follow with all their might and maine: who were intercepted by them of <hi>Carlſtat</hi> and the <hi>Koppreunitzers,</hi> &amp; forced them to leaue the Bridge: And the Turkes, which were on the other ſhoare, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bored in the meane while to breake down the Bridge, whome our people with their ſhott forced to retire.</p>
            <p>When the Turkes perceiued, that the Bridge was taken from them, they tooke the water, which at that tyme was great, and ranne ſo ſtill, as if it had bene a ſtanding lake. In which many a ſtately, worthy and renowned Turke and horſe, loſt his lyfe; for they no ſooner entred it, but were preſently drowned.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:10394:4"/>
            <p>Of all theſe Turkes, very fewe or none eſcaped the water, by reaſon of the ſhot which continually plaid vpon them, all that day and night.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Haſſam Baſſa</hi> of <hi>Boſſna,</hi> him ſelfe with certayne o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Beegen, Aggen, Spahyen, Sayen,</hi> alſo other renow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Turkes, were forced to take the water euen vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>Syſſek,</hi> and were there drowned.</p>
            <p>The high Almains would not take any Turke pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner, but ſlewe them all: but they of <hi>Windeſmarke,</hi> tooke ſome and brought them from thence.</p>
            <p>The Turkes which were on thother ſyde of the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter greatly lamented, and entreated that if their <hi>Baſſa</hi> were taken priſoner, they would not touch his life, but rather honorably entertaine him, for their Emperour would aſſuredly ranſome him.</p>
            <p>The Turkiſh Emperoures ſiſters ſonne, called <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemet Beeg,</hi> ſtretched forth his hand in the water (cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinge as it were to be relieued) but he was preſently ſlayne with a ſhott.</p>
            <p>The bodyes of <hi>Baſſa, Ernot Beeg: Rhuſtan Beeg: and Mehemet Beeg:</hi> who was cheefe Generall of the Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiſh Cauallerie, were taken out of the water, and the ſaid <hi>Mehemet</hi> had his head preſently ſtrooke of.</p>
            <p>The Almaine footemen, &amp; ſuch as were vnder the conduct and leading of <hi>Ferdinand Werdners,</hi> were not preſent at this encounter: but were left behinde to guarde th'Artillery: who forced th'ennemie to leaue eight Field peeces vpon carriages (which were vnder the charge of the <hi>Kazianerins,</hi> and taken from vs by th'ennemy <hi>Anno</hi> 33. before <hi>Eſſek</hi>) and alſo certaine f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> conetes, with thirty ſhippes of Victual: they tooke ſpoyle likewiſe of the whole Campe and riffled <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:10394:5"/> tyltes.</p>
            <p>Thus hath almightie God wonderfully protected the chriſtian ſoldiers (which in number were nothing comparable to thoſe of the Turkes.</p>
            <div type="report">
               <head>
                  <hi>ACCORDING TO THE REPORT</hi> of the Turkes, which were taken priſoners, the Baſſa had then of his owne ſouldiers, men and houſhold people, as followeth.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>FIrſt. In men. 4000</item>
                  <item>Rhamathon Beeg. 1000</item>
                  <item>Berth Beeg of Kliſs. 3000</item>
                  <item>Zeiueri Memy Beeg. 1500</item>
                  <item>Seffer Beeg of Zerink, brother to the Baſſa in Boſsna. 700</item>
                  <item>Beeg of Hertzoguina, ſonne to Achmat Baſsa of the Portes. 3000</item>
                  <item>Kurth Beeg, ſonne to Ferhat Baſsa. 1500</item>
                  <item>Rhuſtan Beeg, of Petrina. 500</item>
                  <item>Ibrohim Beeg, of Likaw. 2000</item>
                  <item>Captaine of Gratiſchko. 1000</item>
                  <item>The number of the other Spahyen, Sayen and land people were. 20000</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:10394:5"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
